Finding Aid for St. Mary Student Parish (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records, 1915-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Mary Student Parish (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records 1915-2000
St. Mary Student Parish (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
10.5 linear feet
85364 Ba 2
Catholic chapel (later parish) ministering largely to University of Michigan students. Council minutes, correspondence, topical files, chapel bulletins, and financial records; also files relating to the Gabriel Richard Foundation, and the Newman Club; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by St. Mary Student Parish (donor no. 5601 ) in 1981. Periodic additions have been made.
The record group is open to research.
St. Mary Student Chapel (now Parish) of the Immaculate Conception (Ann Arbor) traces its origin to 1914 when the auxiliary bishop of Detroit appointed Father Michael Patrick Bourke to begin organizing a separate congregation for Catholic students attending the University of Michigan. Catholic students on campus at that time numbered approximately 600, and it was felt time to provide a facility for their "religious welfare." The first site of the chapel was the Morris property on the southwest corner of Jefferson and State streets which had been secured on March 26, 1915. The Morris home was soon inadequate to meet the needs of the growing Catholic student population, and thus a fund-raising program for the construction of a new building was initiated. Owing to a decision of the University's Board of Regents in 1922 under their power of "eminent domain" to condemn the proposed site of the chapel for state use, Father Bourke, who had been appointed chaplain of the "University Chapel" on April 12, 1919, was forced to secure a second site on which to build. With the moneys raised, he subsequently purchased a parcel of land on the northeast corner of William and Thompson streets for the sum of 29 thousand dollars. Construction of the chapel began in July 1923, and was completed on April 7, 1924 with the laying of the cornerstone. The Student Chapel was officially dedicated on February 29, 1925.
A Newman Club was organized at the Chapel in 1930. Taking its name from the famous English Catholic theologian of the 19th century, the first Newman Club had originated at the University of Pennsylvania in 1893 and soon spread westward. The purpose of the Club at the University of Michigan was "to sponsor the educational and social phases of the Chapel program." The club at the University was reorganized in the mid-1930s, and the first meeting of the modern Newman Club was held on January 23, 1938. On March 5, 1939, the Club began the publication of its bulletin, the Chapel Chronicle.
The subsequent growth of the Newman Club made necessary the building of a facility which could both serve as a student center and as the home of the Newman activities. The Father Gabriel Richard Center was the inspiration of Father Frank J. McPhillip, who coordinated a highly successful nation-wide fundraising campaign among Catholic alumni of the University. The building was formally dedicated November 22, 1953.
The records of St. Mary Student Parish are divided into six series: (1) St. Mary Chapel administrative files; (2) Gabriel Richard Center records; (3) Newman Club records; (4) Miscellaneous records; (5) Newsletters; and (6) Photographs, Scrapbooks, and Albums.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Catholic Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; St. Mary Student Parish (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Religion.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Catholic churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Construction industry.; St. Mary Student Parish (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Religion.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files
  The earliest records within the St. Mary Chapel administrative files series are fragmentary and incomplete. For the years 1921 to 1942, the only surviving documentation are three volumes containing listings of Sunday pulpit announcements. There is greater information for the period since 1942, including correspondence with the archdiocese of Detroit, and correspondence relating to the Gabriel Richard Fundraising Drive. Of interest is correspondence of Father John Fauser between 1967 and 1969, which provides an idea of the changing role of the church and worship format in relation to the social upheavals of the 1960s. The period of 1969 to 1979 is covered in greater detail largely because of the creation of the Chapel Council whose minutes are part of this collection.
  - Historical material (Box 1)
  - Newspaper accounts and other materials relating to the founding and early history of St. Mary Chapel (Box 1)
  - Sunday Announcements, bound volumes
    - 1921-1926 (Box 1)
    - 1926-1932 (Box 1)
    - 1932-1942 (Box 1)
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Goals and objectives (Box 1)
  - By-Laws and revisions (Box 1)
  - Council minutes
    - Undated 1969-June 1978, 34 folders (Box 1)
    - August 1978-April 1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Election Commission (Council)
    - 1970 (first council) (Box 2)
    - Publicity 1970-1973 (Box 2)
    - Election results 1971-1976 (Box 2)
    - Schedules and election forms (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Council notes (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (arranged chronologically)
    - 1924-1953 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1968 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1975 (Box 2)
    - 1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - Undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (arranged alphabetically)
    - Bradley, Fr. John
      - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
      - 1959-1966 (Box 2)
      - 1967 (Box 2)
    - Catholic Social Services 1971-1976 (Box 2)
    - Class correspondence 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - Fauser, Fr. John J. 1967-1969 (Box 2)
    - Open letters to students 1960-1976 (Box 2)
    - Open letters to parents 1965-1974 (Box 2)
    - Religious housing 1964, 1965, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Schumaker, Hazen 1970 (Box 2)
    - Students and faculty 1949-1967 (Box 2)
    - Thank-you letters (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (mimeographed communications from Archdiocese of Detroit)
    - 1941-1953, 13 folders (Box 2)
    - 1954-1968, 14 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous diocesan letters (Box 3)
  - Student newsletters (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous bulletins (Box 3)
  - Topical files
    - Announcements
      - 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Building Committee
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1952 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1964-1967 (Box 3)
      - Leases 1971-1977 (Box 3)
      - Minutes: Architecture and Design Committee 1966 (Box 3)
      - Specifications (Box 3)
      - Valuation report (Box 3)
    - Calendars (Box 3)
    - CCD program (Confraternity of Christian Doctrine) (Box 3)
    - Chapel Council (BEDL: Black Economic Development League) (Box 3)
    - Chapel Council (Christian Service Committee) (Box 3)
    - Chapel Guild (Box 3)
    - Christian Family Movement
      - General (Box 3)
      - Cana Day (Box 3)
    - Commitment-to-poor (Box 3)
    - Deferred sentence (juvenile employment) (Box 3)
    - Diocesan reports (Box 3)
    - Diocesan Service Appeal (Box 3)
    - Faculty addresses (Box 3)
    - Job descriptions (Box 3)
    - Marriage Preparation 1976-1978, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Medical Ethics (Box 4)
    - Notre Dame Law School (Box 4)
    - Religious Housing 1959-1968 (Box 4)
    - Retreat notes (Box 4)
    - Student address list (Box 4)
    - Students killed (W.W.II) (Box 4)
    - Synod
      - Clergy (Box 4)
      - Community affairs (Box 4)
      - Ecumenical affairs (Box 4)
      - Education (Box 4)
      - Laity (Box 4)
      - Missionary (Box 4)
      - Religious (Box 4)
      - Worship (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Tithing Committee (Box 4)
    - Tithing 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - Wedding chapel deposits (Box 4)
    - Weimar, Kathryn (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Financial records
    - Annual financial reports
      - 1939-1945 (Box 4)
      - 1946-1950 (Box 4)
      - 1951-1955 (Box 4)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 4)
      - 1960-1965 (Box 4)
      - 1970-1975 (Box 4)
    - Christian Formation Budget 1973-1977 (Box 4)
    - Council financial accounts 1954-1979, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Development Fund
      - AOF (Archdiocese Development Fund) (Box 4)
      - Bishop's Emergency Relief (Box 4)
      - Christmas (Box 4)
      - Mission Sunday (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Expenditures 1921-1928 (Box 4)
    - Insurance records (Box 4)
    - Operating Statements 1948-1950 (Box 4)
    - Special collections (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1968-1975 (Box 4)
- Gabriel Richard Foundation
  The Gabriel Richard Center series consists primarily of correspondence generated as a result of the fundraising campaign for the construction of the student center. Including topical files and correspondence, this group of records is noteworthy in that it illustrates the capacity of the local Catholic hierarchy to raise money. The correspondence includes letters from automobile and other executives who were active in the alumni fundraising effort.
  - Correspondence (arranged geographically)
    - Alpena and Cheboygan (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 5)
    - Battle Creek (Box 5)
    - Bay City (Box 5)
    - Cadillac (Box 5)
    - Detroit, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Escanaba and Menominee (Box 5)
    - Flint (Box 5)
    - Grand Rapids (Box 5)
    - Houghton and Hancock (Box 5)
    - Iron Mountain (Box 5)
    - Ironwood (Box 5)
    - Jackson (Box 5)
    - Kalamazoo and Benton Harbor (Box 5)
    - Lansing (Box 5)
    - Manistee and Traverse City (Box 5)
    - Monroe (Box 5)
    - Muskegon (Box 5)
    - New York (Box 5)
    - Outstate (Box 5)
    - Pontiac (Box 5)
    - Port Huron (Box 5)
    - Saginaw (Box 5)
    - Sault. Ste. Marie (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (arranged alphabetically)
    - Breitung, Charles A. (Box 5)
    - Coyle, M.E. (Box 5)
    - Doyle, Richard (Box 5)
    - Finn, Thomas R. (Box 5)
    - Harmon, Tom (Box 5)
    - Kelley, Cornelius F. (Box 5)
    - McPhillip, Fr. Frank J. (Box 5)
    - Welch, Richard E. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (arranged chronologically)
    - 1950 (Box 5)
    - 1951 (Box 5)
    - 1952 (Box 5)
    - 1955
      - General (Box 5)
      - Fund raising drive (Box 5)
      - Detroit drive (Box 5)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - 1958-1966 (Box 5)
    - Undated (Box 5)
  - Topical files
    - Financial reports
      - 1950-1953 (Box 5)
      - 1954-1967 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Membership lists, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Report data (Box 6)
    - Student organization (Box 6)
    - Worker lists (Detroit) 1955 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Newman Club
  The Newman Club records are more fragmented, and provide little insight into the early history of the Club. The period since the revision of the constitution and by-laws in 1956 are documented in greater detail.
  - Constitution and by-laws 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - Minutes
    - 1938 (Box 6)
    - 1939-1942, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - 1962 (Box 6)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 6)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - 1971 (Box 6)
    - 1972 (Box 6)
    - 1973 (Box 6)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 6)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 6)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - 1963-1979 (Box 6)
    - Annual reports to Archbishop 1962-1967 (Box 6)
    - Archdiocese of Detroit 1961-1968 (Box 6)
    - Biafra relief 1968 (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
  - Bulletins 1963-1966 (Box 6)
  - Topical files (arranged alphabetically)
    - Archdiocesan staff meetings 1966-1968 (Box 6)
    - Catholic Voices (Box 6)
    - Catholic Voices (correspondence) (Box 6)
    - Class Program Diocesan Service Appeal (Box 6)
    - Education
      - Attendance records (Box 6)
      - Class programs (Box 6)
    - Faculty (Box 6)
    - Family life bureau (Box 6)
    - Financial records
      - 1938-1943 (Box 6)
      - 1969-1980 (Box 6)
      - Education account 1967-1968 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Foreign students (Box 6)
    - Gabriel Richard Center (Box 6)
    - Human Potential seminar (Box 6)
    - International Center
      - Announcements (Box 6)
      - Spanish mass program (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - "Jesus Christ Superstar" (Box 6)
    - Michigan Catholic Conference 1966-1969, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Pastoral Days 1967 (Box 7)
    - Sign-up lists (Box 7)
    - Social action (Box 7)
    - Songs (Box 7)
    - Work-study (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Chronological files
    - 1946 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1968 (Box 7)
    - 1969 (Box 7)
    - Winter 1971 (Box 7)
    - Winter 1972 (Box 7)
    - Fall 1973 (Box 7)
    - Winter 1973 (Box 7)
    - Fall 1974 (Box 7)
    - Winter 1974 (Box 7)
    - Fall 1975 (Box 7)
    - Winter 1975 (Box 7)
    - Fall 1976 (Box 7)
    - Winter 1976 (Box 7)
    - 1977 (Box 7)
    - 1977-1978, undated (Box 7)
    - Winter 1978 (Box 7)
    - Winter 1979 (Box 7)
    - Undated (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes topical files, not clearly generated by either the Newman Club or the Student Chapel. This material consists in part of reports and minutes of various other ecumenical campus organizations, and printed materials of various state and national Catholic organizations.
  - Topical files
    - Abortion, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Association of Religious Counselors (Box 8)
      - 1953-1968, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - North Campus Committee 1956-1967, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Religious Curriculum Committee 1963-1964 (Box 8)
      - Printed material (Box 8)
    - Campus Ministry notes (Box 8)
    - Ecumenical guidelines (Box 8)
    - Education 1961 (Box 8)
    - Faith and Thought lecture series 1993-1994 (Box 8)
    - Interfaith Council
      - Architecture and Design (Box 8)
      - Board minutes (Box 8)
      - Building Fund (Box 8)
      - Newsletters (Box 8)
      - North Campus notes (Box 8)
      - North Campus specifications (Box 8)
    - 50th Jubilee 1974 (Box 8)
    - 75th Jubilee 1999 (Box 8)
    - New Student Welcome materials (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 8)
    - Sermons, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - United Farm Workers (Box 8)
    - Vacation folder (Box 8)
    - Volunteer information (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Newsletters
  Newsletters include parish, archdiocesan, and campus bulletins published during the period from 1966 to 2000.
  - Archdiocesan newsletters 1966-1978, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - "Campus Connection" newsletters 1994-2001 (Box 9)
  - Chapel bulletins 1967-1993, 18 folders (Box 9)
  - Chapel bulletins 1994-2000, 7 folders (Box 10)
- Photographs, Scrapbooks, Albums
  The Photographs, Scrapbooks, and Albums series contains photographs and newspaper clippings related to church events, building construction, and significant clergy members.
  - Photographs
    - Church Officials (Box 10)
    - Construction (Box 10)
    - Interiors (Box 10)
    - Exteriors (Box 10)
    - Foreign Students (Box 10)
    - Groups (Box 10)
    - Hungarian Refugees (Box 10)
    - Youth Outings (Box 10)
    - 1959 photos (Box 10)
    - 50th Jubilee 1974 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Slides (Box 10)
    - Negatives (Box 10)
  - Albums and Scrapbooks
    - Doings around the Newman Club 1947-1948 (Box 10)
    - Winter Retreat February 3-5, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Koinonia One November 2-4, 1990 (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook 1952-1959 (Box 11)
    - Album 1957-1958 (Box 11)
    - Newman Club
      - Clippings 1930-1940 (Box 11)
      - Scrapbook 1947-1948 (Box 11)
      - Scrapbook 1962-1963 (Box 11)
    - Jubilee 1974 (Box 11)
    - Fall Retreat 1987 (Box 11)
Related Material
Newsletters of the parish dated before 1966 and after 2000 have been separately cataloged and are available in the library's printed collection.